<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter id="language" lang="es">
    <title>Idioma</title>

    <para>Un etiquetado consistente crea un entorno familiar por el que el usuario puede navegar confortablemente. Cuanto más familiar sea el entorno, más fácil es encontrar información.</para>

    <sect1 id="language-labels">
      <title>Etiquetas</title>
      
      <sect2 id="language-controls"> 
	<title>Controles</title> 
	<para>Clear, consistent and concise labelling of controls helps users to work out the purpose of a window or dialog they have never seen before. To a visually-impaired user, clear labels are even more important. A user who relies on a screenreader has no assistance from icons, layout, or spacing to work out what the controls do, so clear labelling is essential.</para>
	
	<itemizedlist><title>Guías</title> 
	  <listitem><para>Mantenga las etiquetas cortas. Esto: <itemizedlist> 
		<listitem><para>Reduces the expansion of text when translated, and thus minimizes the effort required to localize the UI. Translated English text can expand up to 30% in some languages.</para></listitem> 
		
		<listitem><para>Facilita el uso de motores de traducción.</para></listitem> 
		<listitem><para>Mejora la velocidad de comprensión para el usuario.</para></listitem> 
	      </itemizedlist></para>
	    
	    <para>Do not shorten your labels to the point of losing meaning, however. A three-word label that provides clear information is better than a one-word label that is ambiguous or vague. Try to find the fewest possible words to satisfactorily convey the meaning of your label.</para></listitem> 
	  
	  <listitem><para>Do not include text in windows that describes <emphasis>how</emphasis> to use the interface, for example <guilabel>You can install a new theme by dropping it here</guilabel>.  As well as adding visual clutter, descriptive labels can also conflict with information provided in documentation.</para></listitem> 
	  
	  <listitem><para>Use standard terms.  You can find a list of standard user interface terms in the <ulink url="http://developer.gnome.org/gdp-style-guide/stable/wordlist.html.en">GNOME Documentation Style Guide, Recommended Terminology</ulink>.</para></listitem> 
	  
	  <listitem><para>Aplique reglas de capitalización estándar. Consulte la <xref linkend="layout-capitalization"/> para obtener consejos sobre la capitalización de las etiquetas de la interfaz de usuario</para></listitem> 
	</itemizedlist>

      </sect2> 
      
      <sect2> 
	<title>Consejos</title> 
	
	<sect3>
	  <title>Consejos de la barra de herramientas</title>
	  
	  <para>Un consejo de barra de herramientas en una descripción corta de la funcionalidad de control de barra de herramientas que el usuario ve al colocar el ratón sobre él.</para>

	  <itemizedlist> <title>Guías</title>
	    <listitem><para>Concisely state the purpose of the control.  The tooltip should be more descriptive than the corresponding menu item name, if there is one, but not verbose.  For example, <guilabel>Undo last action</guilabel> for the <guibutton>Undo</guibutton> button.</para></listitem> 

	    <listitem><para>Use reglas de capitalización en oraciones. Consulte la <xref linkend="layout-capitalization"/>.</para></listitem> 
	  </itemizedlist>            
	  
	</sect3> 
	
	<sect3>
	  <title>Consejos de la aplicación</title> 

	  <para>Un consejo de aplicación es la descripción corta de su aplicación que el usuario ve cuando pasa el ratón sobre el lanzador o elemento del menú para su aplicación. Está almacenada en el campo <structfield>comment</structfield> de su archivo <filename>.desktop</filename> de su aplicación. Consulte la <xref linkend="menu-item-tooltips"/></para>

	  <itemizedlist><title>Guías</title> 
	    <listitem><para>Create short tooltips. Aim to accurately communicate the functionality of an element with the fewest words possible.</para></listitem> 
	    <listitem><para>Use reglas de capitalización en oraciones. Consulte la <xref linkend="layout-capitalization"/>.</para></listitem> 
	    
	    <listitem><para>Use las reglas de puntuación estándar, con la excepción de que no debe usar el punto al final del consejo o sugerencia.</para></listitem> 
	    
	  </itemizedlist> 
	</sect3> 
      </sect2> 
      
      
      <sect2> 
	<title>Menús</title> 
	
	<itemizedlist> <title>Guías</title>
	
	  <listitem><para>Use the recommended standard labels for menu items and titles, where they exist. Do not use synonyms such as <guimenuitem>Exit</guimenuitem> instead of <guimenuitem>Quit</guimenuitem>. See <xref linkend="menus-standard"/> for a list and descriptions of standard menu items and titles.</para></listitem>

	  <listitem><para>Use reglas de capitalización de la cabecera para todos los elementos del menú y títulos. Para obtener más información consulte la <xref linkend="layout-capitalization"/>.</para></listitem> 
	    
	</itemizedlist> 
	
      </sect2>
      
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="language-errors">
      <title>Avisos y mensajes de error</title>
	<para>Un buen aviso o mensaje de error contiene dos elementos:</para>
	<orderedlist>
		<listitem><para>Una breve descripción del problema.</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>Una lista de las formas en las que el usuario puede solucionar el problema.</para></listitem>
	</orderedlist>

	<para>Ambos elementos se deberían presentar en un lenguaje no técnico, libre de jergas, a menos que el público al que está dirigido sea particularmente técnico.</para>

	<para>If your application knows enough about the problem to be able to give all this information to the user, it will often be capable of rectifying the problem itself when the user has decided which course of action they want to take.  For example, if the problem is insufficient memory, tell the user which currently-running application is taking up the most memory, and provide a button to close it for them.  (Do not offer to launch a graphical process manager, however, which is something most users should never see!)</para>

	<para>Consulte la <xref linkend="windows-alert"/> para obtener información más detallada acerca de escribir y presentar errores, avisos y alertas de información.</para>
    </sect1>


    <sect1 id="language-help">
      <title>Ayuda en línea</title>
	<para>Writing online help is a specialized task, and is therefore not covered in any depth here.  Refer to the <ulink url="http://developer.gnome.org/gdp-style-guide/stable/">GNOME Documentation Styleguide</ulink> for guidance on writing clear, consistent and helpful documentation for your application.</para>
    </sect1>

  </chapter>
